Finding Aid for Helen Hill papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Helen Hill Papers 1976-2012, 1987-1995
Hill, Helen, 1915-
1 oversize folders
2 linear feet
2015030 Aa 2 Ac
A writer and retired English professor, Helen Hill helped found Trailblazers, a clubhouse rehabilitation center for the mentally ill in Washtenaw County, Michigan. Most of Hill's papers relate to the operations of the Trailblazers and include bylaws, financial records and reports, meeting materials, fliers, brochures, newsletters, correspondence and subject files relating to mental illness. The collection also contains records of Hill's involvement with other organizations dedicated to mental health services.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Helen Hill (donor no. 11200 ), in three accessions between November 2014 and January 2015.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Helen Hill is a writer, editor, and retired professor. Born in Brooklyn, New York in 1915, she received her Bachelor of Arts from Wheaton College in Massachusetts in 1936 and a Master of Arts from Brown University in 1937. In 1941, she married Donald L. Hill, with whom she had four children. Hill moved to Ann Arbor, Michigan with her husband in 1948. She worked as an editorial assistant at the University of Michigan on Smithsonian Institution: Ars Orientalis from 1959 until 1963, when she was hired as a Professor of English at Eastern Michigan University in Ypsilanti. She taught at Eastern Michigan University until 1984. While working as a professor of English, Hill co-edited multiple anthologies of poetry for children and young adults. Even after retiring from teaching, Hill remained an active writer and researcher. In 1995, she published a book entitled A Proud and Fiery Spirit, a narrative which drew on the letters and journals of her grandfather, a sea captain from Duxbury, Massachusetts named Edward Baker. The book was published by the Duxbury Rural and Historical Society.
While attending a Community Mental Health organization education seminar for parents of children with mental illness in the fall of 1983, Hill, her husband, and other parents attending the seminar took note of the lack of local drop-in centers or agencies providing housing and jobs for people with mental illness. In 1984, Hill and her husband took action, working with friends from the seminar to found the Washtenaw County Chapter of the National Association for the Mentally Ill (NAMI). Hill served as Vice President of the Alliance for the Mentally Ill (AMI) of Washtenaw County for the terms of 1984-1985 and 1986-1987, and Treasurer in 1985-1986. She was an AMI of Washtenaw County Board member from 1989 to 1993. In August 1989, with members of AMI and other friends, Helen and Donald Hill coordinated the founding of Trailblazers, a psychosocial rehabilitation center modeled on Fountain House in New York. Fountain House was the first 'clubhouse' rehabilitation center of its kind, providing the mentally ill with a community support system as well as a work-ordered day to help them regain their sense of self-worth and confidence. The Trailblazers' clubhouse was designed to help the chronically mentally ill find employment and reintegrate into life in the local community.
In 1993, Hill returned to teaching, giving courses in memoir writing at the Osher Lifelong Learning Institute (OLLI) at the University of Michigan. She retired from OLLI in December 2014.
The collection is organized into two series: Trailblazers of Washtenaw County and Other Non-Profit Organizations for Mental Health Services.
The Helen Hill papers document her extensive involvement with the Trailblazers and other non-profit organizations providing services and advocacy for people with mental illness. The papers also include select published and unpublished literature on mental illness and contemporary models for psychosocial rehabilitation.
Subjects:
Alliance for the Mentally Ill of Washtenaw County.; Hill, Helen, 1915-; Mentally ill--Care--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; NAMI Michigan.; Trailblazers of Washtenaw County.
- Trailblazers of Washtenaw County
  The Trailblazers of Washtenaw County series (1.5 linear feet, 1987-1996) documents Hill's activities in her roles as founder and president, vice president, and treasurer at different stages in time. The Trailblazers series also traces the development of the Trailblazers as an organization through proposal summaries, financial reports, bylaws, personnel policies, and promotional literature. The series is divided into six components: Grant Proposals, Administrative Records, Clubhouse Materials, Meeting Materials, Promotional Materials, Resolutions, and Subject Files. Grant Proposals includes requests for grant funding and proposal summaries from the period of the founding of the Trailblazers. Administrative Records include summary financial information and operational records. Clubhouse Materials encompass records from the process of choosing a site for the clubhouse as well as literature on clubhouse models for psychosocial rehabilitation, an approach to rehabilitation emphasizing community living, skill development, and pre-vocational training as a means to helping the chronically mentally ill regain their individual sense of self-worth. Meeting Materials include Minutes, Agendas, and Memoranda. Promotional Materials include the Trailblazers' newsletters, local news editorials, brochures, fliers, and concise organizational histories written by Hill. Resolutions consist of government tributes accorded to the Hills in recognition of their work with the mentally ill. The Subject Files encompass articles on mental health rehabilitation, Hill's reading lists, and first person accounts of the experience of mental illness.
  - Grant Proposals
    - 1989-1991, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Administrative Records
    - Financial
      - Budgets 1990-1992, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Fund Letters 1990-1993 (Box 1)
      - Fundraising 1989-1993 (Box 1)
      - Treasurer's Reports 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - Operational
      - Bylaws undated (Box 1)
      - Personnel Policy 1993-1997 (Box 1)
  - Clubhouse Materials
    - Ann Arbor Citizens' Council Clubhouse Model 1988 (Box 1)
    - Clubhouse Standards 1989-1992 (Box 1)
    - Drawing of Clubhouse (Folder 1)
    - Model Projects, Case Studies 1976-1992, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - PSR Program Pamphlet 1988 (Box 1)
    - Site Selection 1988-1992, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Meeting Materials
    - Agendas, Minutes 1987-1996 (Box 2)
    - Minutes 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - Minutes 1995 (Box 2)
    - PSR Memos and Minutes 1987-1989 (Box 2)
  - Promotional Materials
    - Ann Arbor News Editorials 1989 (Box 2)
    - Brochures, Fliers 1985-1992 (Box 2)
      (Includes one photograph)
    - Fact Sheets 1984-1993 (Box 2)
    - Newsletters 1992-1994, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Videocassette, Master Broadcast Videocassette (Box 2)
  - Resolutions
    - Resolution Honoring Helen and Donald Hill 1993 (Folder 1)
    - Senate Concurrent Resolution No. 151 1995 (Folder 1)
  - Subject Files
    - Articles on Rehabilitation
      - Articles by Dincin (Box 2)
      - Articles by Hecker (Box 2)
      - Articles by Propst (Box 2)
    - Bibliographies, Reading Lists (Box 2)
    - First Person Accounts 1987-1988 (Box 2)
    - Tie Lines Bulletin, 1998 (Box 2)
- Other Non-Profit Organizations for Mental Health Services
  The Other Non-Profit Organizations for Mental Health Services series (0.5 linear feet, 1987-2012) provides evidence of Hill's involvement with the Alliance for the Mentally Ill and the Mental Illness Advisory Council, as well as her interest in programs for Assertive Community Treatment (ACT). The records and printed materials in this series have been separated into groups according to organization. Materials in this series include bylaws, newsletters, and meeting materials related to the Alliance for the Mentally Ill, a report and outreach materials from the National Alliance for the Mentally Ill, meeting materials from the Mental Illness Advisory Council, and reviews of Assertive Community Treatment programs.
  - Alliance for the Mentally Ill
    - Bylaws, Organizational Structure, Miscellaneous, Logos 1989-1992, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - AMI Newsletters 1990-2012 (Box 2)
    - Agendas, Meeting Materials 1992-1993 (Box 2)
  - Assertive Community Treatment Programs 1987-1988 (Box 2)
  - Mental Illness Advisory Council 1987-1989 (Box 2)
  - National Alliance for the Mentally Ill
    - Annual Report 1996 (Box 2)
    - Advocacy, outreach 1992-2009 (Box 2)
Related Material
The Bentley holds additional material related to NAMI including:
Archival Material
Kevin Duke papers (another Trailblazers Founder,)
NAMI Michigan records
NAMI Eastside Support Group records (catalog record)
Printed periodicals and publications, cataloged separately
NAMI Michigan news: from around the state,
NAMI Metro: Oakland, Wayne and Macomb Counties.
History of NAMI Michigan, by Hubert C. Huerbel